thank you
um where we were again the last lecture
uh so we were considering a gaussian
type uh hat in the world where the uh
the related versions uh where uh our uh
variable was this appeal of this week
for his time uh and we considered the
case where the action could be
originated in this very general form you
can tell uh
where a is on a differential operator uh
so foreign
uh and the main result would be right
last time with that this thing is equal
to actually G of L1 is now two where G
is the nuclear internal the appear in
the inverse of the operative a so uh so
here this G but that's that a reverse I
can do a Tau uh it's supposed to be
integral detailed Prime g t Prime uh
Prime and uh uh you know in this case
for example uh it follows that the gene
would have to pay the equation that if
you take this dimensional operator say
just look at the Delta functions
um
uh and uh let me just uh carry on this
one more step uh this G uh in the case
of times agrees with the form of G I
wrote previously you haven't used the
same letter and it was actually the same
function so you see
um I can solve this equation uh by oh
yeah times one it's right on the answer
and it's easy to verify that the
solution to this equation uh is such
that D is equal to integral APK over 2i
and this Romans Infinity of uh e to the
i k times
over a case where plus Omega squared
so you can easily verify this because if
you take the dimension operator and act
on this thing here in the integrand
right you just pull down a k square plus
Omega Square tons of government this is
gone and the integral is just means
so at the beginning of Last Action we
did all that work but with some finite
times T minus capital T and we took some
limit and we got the answer but that's
actually can be reproduced by this you
don't have to
all right uh any questions about this so
far
all right so uh now let me just make a
comment about uh this expression value
um I've explained this yeah
this like the whole I mean the whole
person that we did um
correlation like the whole body like
when you don't want the normal season
budget right or well there's one just to
have been divided into these two right
so it's really nice in the measure
now uh
uh I hope you remember the physical
origin of this we had a different
interpretation levels there's one in
some kind of statistical average in our
original interpretation this came from
the analyticulation about actual Matrix
elements all right let's recall
so uh value from the left-hand side is
actually equal to
um
before
you missed that from our previous
discussion okay so uh
the way we derived this last time you
know there's no how and how to or
arbitrary right but the client said in
order to write this as a matrix elements
uh with this Q being the anti Convention
of the uh the original queue to UK and
time to do the time tab uh but this
right inside only actually makes sense
with power too fantasy recall it only
follows one power great and help you why
was that
um uh it's because if you if you spell
this out in a little more detail you see
the right hand side if I plug into this
way of writing that you had a Tau it's
um you saw that it's not now uh foreign
foreign
[Music]
and this is going to diverge
exponentially and the sound that will be
only fine so 84 right uh you know this
query generic system uh this right hand
side would only be well defined
um but in case I'm not answering some
coincidence because actually most of
these all except one-time Dropout but in
that case it doesn't matter so much but
generally you should understand this way
uh just don't make this just to say this
in a different way
um in the
um in the way I wrote this path of the
world uh uh the the you know there's no
watering okay without two and by
definition these are some very intuition
variable so by definition
the same the same in the middle of there
no difference like definition doesn't
care about the weather but the right
hand side in this case is only to be
bind with a state reporter the other one
is it doesn't make sense this operator
back on the vacuum if it's Taiwan it's
better than how two the sequence of
foreign
uh the real time
many I have a choice notation but
whenever I write key it's real time
it's uh it's uh uh it's the imaginary
the quicker time right so so this real
time QT this is supposed to be a pizza
that uh i h e u h
minus five
um and uh for this in a usual quantum
mechanics uh this you have here the
permission operator and this major
element are well defined real time if
you want these two so this is defined uh
without any restrictions uh you want to
do
um as it should be
um but uh the thing is that these two
lines often is not compute General
and uh we discussed a particular
instance where you can perform this
energy potential and release this uh to
this with a specific order of common
something
okay so so you know if you find this uh
confusing you know always go back to the
definition and see what's going on I'd
like to think more about this
yourself
but the point is that we have to be a
little careful of the different objects
which are closely related but
conceptually different than what I've
been talking about there's their Matrix
elements of these uh the skill height
operators uh evolved in real time
there's this uh which is related
calculation and then there are these
significant values computed from the
which are they pathway and as you see
they're closely related but they're not
exactly
the one we should look at
the little property they're full
but sorry what would you say okay
there's another thing
oh you're the time boilers uh let's post
on that discussion uh so far you know
you can Define whatever you want you can
choose to you know multiply this by some
functions
um but of course you know as a some
function that capture the information
the Spectrum the theory like so they are
not independent uh the time ordered
object will have some specific use
um the contents but let's post on that
discussion because so far it's not
obvious why that's a that's a useless
uh let me just say that so far I'm going
to discussed Ace visit evaluation that
works uh if you want to do something
different you have to uh you have to
show that it works well you close the
controvers uh let's talk about the
discussion because in order to explain
pictures so they take some time and this
is uh not necessary for what I'm about
to say
any other questions about this
uh what what this discuss the another
property of these teleporting functions
in the actual Quantum filter context a
more detail later but for now I will
only uh say what I what I actually read
soon
what
um
uh and let me just uh uh
uh make the additional remark that uh
this quantity here of course we actually
can do last time this is actually using
the radio formula this whole integral is
uh one over two Omega e to the minus
Omega is
whenever I write command two is
and uh if you compare it to this
normally you see that this Omega is
indeed that the difference between E1
and e0 so that agrees
that guy said that's very very simple
right we just get a single exponential
in general if there's a q hat zero and
the grass and has overlapped with the
other excited states you have the sum of
a bunch of exponential not just a single
explanation
uh this kind of thing over in the
content called the special decomposition
uh we'll have more to say about that
later
okay so uh
to example example two we're going to
discuss the first example so now the
second example uh after oscillator is uh
the N Harmony
is not harmonic
um so so what is this well this is a
specific thing that's okay instead of
this squared plus uh oh so um I'm going
to uh set this Omega uh also to one for
the for the sake of discussion because
uh you know here I keep track of this
frequency omega-coming oscillator but
the uh for the for from now you know we
don't need to worry too much about that
I'm just going to set that to one so the
harmonic acid will just be uh described
with hamiltonian P Squared however two
plus Q Square over two uh then I'm going
to add a quartic potential sorry
something like Q to the fourth uh but
just for the sake of convenience our
normalize this conversion should be some
can be constant G over four factorial
this is just a convention so there's
some number G here LG is a
so the G is there is some coupling
constants
uh it's just a conversion of a recording
terminal potential
okay
um so uh as a a system of quantum
mechanics uh you know how to study this
in principle you know you can solve the
energy levels by selling showing the
equation by normalizable and so forth
right so the advantage of discussing
this in the Practical language is that
we're always grounded you uh you can
always if you get confused always go
back to your undergrad economy kind of
textbook and figure out how to study
this uh the The Observers of Interest
any kind of uh you know energy Spectrum
or Matrix elements of
observations of interests like this Q
hats exhibition patterns
okay so but now again we're going to
study this using the path integral
okay
um so uh so first step we're going to
write lagrangian uh well that's
straightforward is still the kinetic
term uh minus the potential term right
which is this and uh and of course uh
you know we're going to play the same
game of the week rotated
um which is more convenient for our
purpose uh so
um the euclidean version is just uh one
half Intel Q squared plus squared over
two
okay so any question about the system uh
we are considering for continuing
all right so um once again uh we're
going to uh study uh a quantity like
this
or a computer using pattern to grow as
the president of this qt1 qt2 and
starting the pattern go exactly the same
as well as out here uh all I need to do
is to uh erase so I can actually recycle
this board everything on this board uh
still always except for them or
except that I'm going to erase this
formula okay so so this is very true and
I'm gonna erase of this
but uh but everything else still holds
uh
uh actually no okay
this is the business
foreign
okay so um so now if you are actually
able to calculate you see this uh two
point expression value you will be able
to read out information about the energy
spectrum of this Theory and the energy
spectrum of this oscillator well does
anyone know the switch what is the
energy eigenvalue of this in terms of G
between the two energy
situations uh no no no no oh let me say
as soon as you impossible so the
potential is like this
right so so let's say
the potential
uh looks like this
okay so so you know we have some energy
levels but whatever is energy levels in
other computes
uh
you can try but
the good news is yes get the provision
Theory values is that it doesn't
converge
but uh but but uh we're gonna try to do
it anyway and uh at some point what this
will come back and revisit uh the
district so yes you can do Hamilton
Theory but we're going to do the
lagrangea version of that
um
right so uh if you know the exact answer
to this two-point query function you
would be able to expand as a uh you know
as some obviously it's a sequence of the
sequence of exponential in principle and
read off and as well so so the capital
of the information you want yeah in this
case uh unlike the harmonic acid which
you had the ground said only had overlap
with the projects United States um
that's no longer true here this here the
cue pattern on the grounds they will
have overlapped with the first executive
State uh uh and uh uh and many an
infinite Tower
further exciting things
um
uh okay
um so
um
uh so uh we we just need to figure out
how to compute uh both the numerator and
the denominator with this uh Action Now
deformed from the from my alternator by
this according
um okay so so how do we do that uh let's
start with uh the denominator
okay so let's start right with this you
just want to do that let's call this the
normally the proximate function uh Z and
let's calculate responding
now certainly speaking uh we are not
going to
um know uh from this the way I probably
in this way there's some ambiguous
normalization uh and uh
um but you'll see uh where this thing
shows up uh but the point is that uh
whatever ambiguity there is It's Gonna
Cancel out in the final answer so not
enough worry too much about the
ambiguity in doing this stage of
computation
um so so let's try
um
uh so uh V is uh
into the uh
until uh so we separate this into two
terms so first we have the harmony
operator uh action which by itself would
be right to a gaussian type functional
integral and then we have the we have e
to the uh minus uh now uh so uh G over
400 kilo count to the fourth
um so
uh uh
right now uh we're just gonna uh well
the only thing we we know how to we
don't even know how to deal with this
anyways at the moment is to uh just
expand exponential so it was small
exponential uh I can rewrite re-express
this as of course the sum a little n
from 0 to Infinity one over and
factorial of uh minus uh some G over
complex operating outside integral
to the board uh
uh and uh
um no
um if you assume
uh if you assume that uh you can't
exchange the order on functional
integral with the sum over little n uh
then we'll be able to conclude this term
by time and each term is of the form of
the equation value well not by the
existing value but it's the the gaussian
integral of a bunch of probably a bunch
of queues and we knew how to do this
last time we introduced this rule of the
wick contraction uh that would allow you
to recover this turn by turn right so if
you can exchange the order of some as an
integral
um but then you can compute this the
right term and then we're in good shape
any questions so far
uh so now uh as most physicists might
have received if I assuming that you can
always
but uh but there's not that it doesn't
work it turns out that you cannot quite
do that uh however there's a sense in
which
um you can uh
the thing is in terms of what happens if
you change the time of the integral
um the sum actually uh
um will not uh actually converge so
we'll have zero radius converters in G
um but
um uh but none of us would be correct
but it captured all the all other series
expansion what happens that the the
actual current function as a function of
of G uh is actually not the real
analytic
um and uh it entire series doesn't
conversion itself
um but for now we're going to ignore
that problem for now we're just knowing
too
um uh but you know this is this is the
extent of which QED device
which means you might but
so so this problem can be partially
cured as you see uh but for now I'm
going to ignore this individual and
Transformers
um
okay
so
um
you can do that and you can exchange the
order of the of the sum and uh uh and
that function integral uh then
um uh we can say that this is the uh at
some value G uh so I'm using the Z sub G
to denote the uh
is it because you have G to denote the
the primary function at a particular
value of G of the copy
um and if I compare this to the very
function as zero copy which will just be
the that of the harmonic oscillator
um then uh that that is just uh equal to
uh the expression value of this quantity
um
zero
uh Theory
it was Zero model
um Q of Tau one uh to the part
uh Q of Tau n
so there's two of zero and I.E the the
the quantum
or are we now integrating over top one
to seven
uh on this experience you know I I'm
just writing this out right I mean you
know I have this integral to n power I I
better change in my variable if I want
to write them as a as a single integral
I I was renaming the variable
and different tasks
all right and and of course as you might
have noted I have secretly exchanged the
the song with the integral uh you know
you might have uh Mr missed that dude if
at the end point it out but but uh you
know these things are actually more
subtle than you might have thought
uh but anyway we're gonna proceed so
this is really importation but we're
going to proceed
management with us
um okay
that's the integral over to cube right
uh that this is integral over at DQ uh
by the weighted by just this action so
so that would be that's why I write a
subscript uh g code zero or in the
officer Theory so so this will be the
extreme value of the product with excuse
uh in the gaussian function interval
yes
remember I'm divided by the two zero
here
how are we able to write and like as a
factor like exactly things now you could
after all we're doing it yourself and
that gas is part still depends on that
right all of the acute house are
different parameters different variables
for every now two times the variable or
something
so you can think of this as that is if
you want uh but uh the talent is labels
which variable we're talking about
they will show something in there of
course I think we're in there
so that's why you wrote it
uh yes ah maybe you're asking why am I
allowed to pull this integral outside of
the
expression value
but I can because uh you know literally
by definition this is just a sum of
different variables
um
by definition you're saying that it's
just going through early there is
execution
yes that is by definition
this thing is integral of detailed one
to tell one to the course zero Utah two
to the part uh and so on and so forth
now
is
that for some of our uh
uh okay so uh now uh so you know we just
took a few of this and this we have
learned from the last lecture that will
get confused from the weak contractions
so we did this one so let's just do that
um
so let's move this border by order uh
the little end
well of course at the living water is
this one right so this whole thing
starts at uh one let's correspond to the
term angle angle zero uh and then
another n goes one what do we have we
have
minus G over four factorial times
integral detail of uh just to tell
uh I'll just write sub square root of
zero this is in the in the theory so
that's again the harmonic acid Theory uh
and uh and then the next one that we
have one half uh minus G over four
factorial uh squared integral detail one
Theta two uh for your value of computers
support
okay so let's look at this uh one at a
time but let's look at this let's
quantity here so what is this
uh well let's remember our rule the last
time I wrote this I wrote u n q m q r q
s uh but that's you know that's how it's
the level just like this n and M
subscripts
um so
um uh so of course
at the same time but that's not uh it
doesn't matter okay so let me just write
this out uh and the liquid contraction
tells us that it's going to calculated
by uh you can track them this way
uh so I represent this by
uh revertise
so every kind of uh um every time I put
down a pack of G I get uh the insertion
of four queues and same value now
um and um uh I'm just going to draw a
diagram uh to keep track of the fact
that every time I have a Vertex accounts
with this coefficient so it comes with
this coefficient uh minus a geode report
so I'm going to associate this this
formula here I'm going to have something
with a graph where this vertex is
represented backpack there's this uh
multiplying this whole thing uh but then
every white line that comes out on the
board from this vertex uh correspond to
a q insertion and these white lines are
tied to at the same point uh this
represents the fact that all the cues
are at the same value of euclidean times
I'm not gonna
keep writing that
um so um
and then
the which contraction
is just some way you can tie these uh
white lines together with uh these
uh bird boxes what I call it a g earlier
there was the inverse of the Matrix a in
the Galaxy integral that I discussed
last time
uh now uh there are three different ways
to do it between practice right so so we
saw that last time but in terms of the
picture we can say that there's this so
you
you draw the vertex you fix these white
lines but then you just can we can
choose different ways to to contract
these this white line together with this
um
G uh so and then there's one more ways
you can connect this with that and this
would
and of course as you might see that they
are actually all identical so you have
three copies
at the same time
and what you actually uh have for the uh
purple line here well this purple line
supposed to represent a cute Tau you
know the community house
um could be a different house but here
it is
so that's according to our goal uh this
was uh G of power and how two I thought
what I'm talking about
uh
uh it was one of our two Omega you know
Omega to one this country is actually
equal to
um
okay uh any questions so far
point so when we didn't work with
children now
the contraction last time we did it as
like a main event e to the Q some Matrix
to right and uh yeah but you remember
the end result of that contraction was
just that excuse now one uh could help
to contraction uh with the same thing as
the extreme value of 3.12 right and then
we just can in the beginning of lecture
we said that
speak of this Matrix
or convince yourself
okay any other questions
um all right so uh so let's put this
together and calculate the like one or
two terms in this expression
uh okay so uh the order G term in this
expansion in the of z uh is just as we
see here minus G over 34 times 3 because
there are three identical diagrams and
each one of them is going to be now G of
Tau Tau squared
uh
yeah
okay
uh so it's good that we calculate this
with another squared uh the the values
is that this appears to be Divergent
because you're integrating uh the
content uh in Tau
all right
uh any questions about this
the complaints
well uh you know we said that you know
we're going to run into some issues with
very toxic but this is going to be uh
in in the immediate stage uh we're going
to interpret this Divergence soon and
figure out a way to to fix the problem
uh in fact this is uh as often occurs
here it's a feature another bug
yes so what is integrated
there is no power two and power one
right I mean this is where it comes from
remember this came from the term in the
action it's just into a detox that was
in action there was no difference
between Taiwan County they're all just
power
compels
right so that's right yeah
any other questions
thank you
um
okay this because in this case how are
how how our knowledgeable they're not
like problems right I mean a towel is a
it's like an index right yeah
uh okay good so so so so we'll revisit
this uh Divergence later and we'll see
what it means
uh we have something uh well okay so
what do we have we have one now uh minus
G over four factorial squared and you
tell one you tell two
um q a one uh to the fourth Q now two to
the fourth uh again completed in the
Galaxy well
um and we're going to uh first turn this
into a picture and send a picture back
to the equation
um
uh so uh well that's all our rule
um so we got two furnaces here
uh one will be you can write 1000 to
remind yourself that the car is going to
be two thirds first one to four cues we
started times how one you quickly Factor
one this four Q is at the top two
and then uh where instructed to consider
uh to sum over all the possible weak
contractions of the eight cubes uh now
there are different types of diagram you
can draw you can contract this way
uh
this is this is one diagram you can draw
the corresponder one term in the weekly
fashion the possible with contractions
uh here's another one you can draw so
um you can contract uh like this
right uh you can also do something like
before you can do
I'm not going to uh
exhaustively diagrams but uh here
there's some examples this all right you
guys draw the possible graphs
uh the contractors and you just have to
add them together now what do this graph
mean well this one again is like GTA one
tell one you know what that means and
here so what is this for example uh this
guy here is G Taiwan
this is g l one L2 this is another g l
one l two where this is G now to the top
two oh this function return no there's
some simple functions that we concluded
earlier and just multiply this together
and multiply the coefficients and then
you add that
okay very simple I have the integrator
which is Divergence but don't worry
about that yeah and
a bit uh any questions about this
all right
um
foreign
function would only be well defined if
you do this integration and finally
range
um and without boundary condition
uh we said that you could take the ratio
it explaining value but this
bonification doesn't matter it will drop
out if you take a limit but if you just
can do the D by itself the publication
doesn't matter your homework problem
with some Iranian population
but that doesn't matter
um so here uh in principle uh we need to
uh put this integral declared some some
range and if we take this range to be
very large but not less uh the a part of
that have to be finite so that would
cause this Divergence okay it's
Divergence
um but in order to understand the
potential interpretation of the project
function uh it's going to be useful to
figure out how we want to reorganize all
the diagrams
um and uh we're going to now do a little
bit of uh combinatorics to figure out uh
how to how we can kind of rearrange all
these uh diagrams here
um as you can see
um some of them so already the second
order in G some other diagrams are are
these are connected
graphs
these graphs are disconnected
okay but you see here that the
disconnect graphs are related graphs in
a very simple way you just multiply a
bunch of clinical graphs together right
this corresponds a term in this
expansion but literally just the product
of this term with that term
okay so
um uh so we're going to uh simplify our
life a little bit uh by trying to
express this whole party function in
terms of just the connected graphs
so uh generally at some order
G to the n
so each write the sound each set of weak
interactions
um
can be
represented
by ignac
so every time whenever I say wrap in
this particular context I mean uh I take
a bunch of these coordinate vertices is
with the four lines coming out and let's
connect the legs with the with this
purple uh purple lines
uh so by a graph that uh
uh consists of
let's say uh K connected to components
[Music]
um and uh among among them
among these kinetic components
um uh let's say Suppose there are for
every l
there are ml uh connected
uh graphs
uh but
uh contained
uh
L vertices
huge
so for example
um
so uh so let's say uh this represents
right there contains some L versus uh
and you can have a another graphic
alvertise another graphical
and the total member of this would be ml
minus one
so
uh
the product yeah I'm talking about a
specific uh so this whole thing is uh
what I've been calling a single rap if I
can book and disconnect so this is a
single graph so the total number the
total number of vertices
um okay
um
so
uh okay so first I I don't understand
the K is the sum of an L uh uh
one uh and N is equal to some L times
okay
uh okay so uh for
uh a given
uh partition
of and according to this pattern so I
separate and it is your end into this uh
subsets of groups of L
um
specified by the MLS
um the
a number
of ways
of grouping
the and vertices
in this matter
like so so you know apri uh the point is
that you know you know this verses I can
I can connect them uh in all possible
ways and I want to look at the uh the
possible ways to arrange them into in a
graph of that
um the number of ways to uh group The
invernesses in this pattern is uh n
factorial over a product L greater than
equal to one
um Alpha factorial to the power and L
times
so basically here is just that I tell
you all the presentation of endpoints uh
m versus uh and I divide Us by the
permutation then leave this computer
should be better so that that is uh
again permits within each group of
albertists and I can produce all these
ml groups of America
so that's a different ways to to uh
uh uh let me try to do this so so you
take you take emphasis and then you uh
you group them into uh into like l in
this first group uh in this movement and
this without any kind of the order of
this uh books of film and for every app
so you you pick your setup you pick
yourself ml right uh
so in this case uh in this case m one is
equal to one and two is equal to zero uh
and uh
okay so we have to take all of this into
account
uh that is arbitrary integer right so
I'm just saying that uh three times
these things add up to the Ten Perfect
so n is arbitrary yeah
okay
um
uh so uh here so the total contributions
uh
thank you
um so what do we have in order to do to
the n to the end order
um we've always got this one over n
factorial from expanding out the
exponential at the beginning right
and uh and then we've got
uh this number of ways of grouping
versus this command factorial over
product okay then one now factorial and
L kind of say no
um and then uh and then I have to uh
take the product of all the actual
graphs each one of it which requires
about the formula in the way I described
earlier so uh but that's now easy to
describe I just have a product over L uh
and g l to the ml power where GL
is the sum of of all graphs
um
uh uh uh
all connected to say in a second all
connected uh with contraction some of
all kinetic graphs
uh that uh
uh the same forms
out of
uh quick interactions
um
of L versus
okay
um
so you know this
discussion is that I'm now rewrite
re-expressing the G to the end the other
contribution which involve both
generally connected disconnect graphs
into just kinetic Labs because after all
I knew that the disconnect graphs are
not Independents from the clinic graph
they're just part of Connecticut graphs
but this is the explosive formula they
express this in terms of just the sum of
the kinetic graphic well L vertices
right so so for example if I got uh well
maybe this is okay so for example if you
have three vertices right
then the G to the L here what
um
uh would contain uh contributions like
like this
so so this is included in the G to the L
but uh something like disconnected
like that
like that this will be uh this will be
discarded here
let me just just say this because again
generally every time the sum every time
every this kind of graph will be of this
part so they're just probably graphs
right so so this is summarizing this
formula so the spirit factors are just
different different ways that are given
the same company that's it
[Music]
I mean you also have the input of the
Taiwan tattooism
good
um all right uh so now uh once you
accept this formula it would be uh
what was to accept this formula
um it's uh you can just sum it up
um so Z
is
uh some uh over all the possible
assignment of MLS uh product so it's the
N factor of cancer right so I can just
write this as uh equivalent as a product
called L greater than or equal to one of
one over ml factorial uh and then one
over and just bring the two two products
together I have one over n factorial and
then have one over L factorial G to the
L to the power and to the L
all right so uh this is the same as a
product okay to the sum for it
independently for each L because ml is
independently every l so sum over h m l
uh from 0 to Infinity one over ml
factorial remember this uh ML and the
the this thing here is exponentials this
is equal to exponentiation exponential
of 1 over l g l
uh so um this is saying that actually uh
if I had taken the log of z g
if I had taken the law of dependent
function it would be like itself but
only keep track of the kinetic wraps
uh any questions about this
so it's saying that the sum over graphs
just actually exponentiates uh and uh if
I just compute the kinetic wraps
is taken care of so yeah I'm doing this
characteristics once for all I mean once
we understand this later you know you'll
understand that kind of whenever you
have this is going to grab they're
always going to explanation in this way
you don't have to calculate by hand of
the it's going to grasp on laboriously
it just follows from expanding this
explanation so when you when you expect
you know just say this again if you
expand this exponential you get a
product of those G's right by explaining
this in return expansion and that part
of the juice is going to take taken
account of all the disconnect graphs
with the exact right commentatorical
positions
uh uh I'm
uh I'm not sure why you need that
interpretation of this uh all I'm
describing here is a way to uh to to
compute the permanent function and I I
said what is connected uh provides are
but so far I've not discussed it's
written value yet I mean uh because this
is
okay
um
uh any other questions
yeah so it's a dumb question like where
does it evolve oh gee it's included in
the graph itself so every vertex every
vertex comes with a factor of minus one
minus G over four factorial
uh so maybe I wasn't very clear about
the uh about the about that but uh
computes some number out of this and
what yeah
um no I'm going to so we have GG values
examples so there but like aren't we
taking a product of the uh main
functions and when we're doing I'm not
going to be a functioning yes right so
far oh sorry my individual graph yes
we're taking that yeah yes yes
I mean that there are different graphs
right like three verses that are
connected right so for example there's
this uh there I can also draw different
program right so so there's that you can
enjoy uh I don't know
and all of the possible ways to contract
the three vertices in the case of L
equal three uh uh as long as the whole
thing remain connected
yeah so you understanding before we're
doing this derivation for part either in
a big series
is example uh oh uh yes I should have
written
thank you
so
this or this right so here I'm summing
over all the possible uh uh
decompositions uh so uh
right so so I'm suddenly over so when I
write the sum over this question of MLS
uh I I'm talking about uh I'm something
over all the possible
um uh uh sequence of integers that that
ordered to enable how many N1 and two
and three so this is some over N1 from
uh zero Infinity M2 from zero two to
zero Fitness and so on and so forth
by definition
it's uh you know I I
um
[Music]
maybe
yeah the difference is this this bracket
right this bracket means that I'm
summing over this entire sequence of uh
integers and one and two and three and
so forth I said yeah I'm just send me
over individual one but inside the
product it's the same
also the first one even to find there's
ml before like L is larger than one
um so
um I you choose M1 a sequence
of the meters right
um uh but the only finally many of them
are not zero uh once you have chosen
that uh you take the product over L and
if you see whatever L is put in oh and
now right that's that's how we derive
this so I mean the point is that
um we are looking at all the possible uh
you know partition of integer and
um in this way and every discipline
graph where can I graph will be labeled
by some exclusive ml cool finally
anyway anyway
let's just do this for n up to five and
you'll give yourself that yeah
um
no GL is around here is the sum of all
kinetic Rock when I say when I when I
say the graph I mean that that the
formula the correspond to grab of course
sure all right so so the sum of all the
kinetic graphs the correspond to
distinct with contractions of Albert is
this but they have to be such that the
whole the result of reconstruction is
results in the graph that's connected
uh while the congratic practice doesn't
have to do with with that itself but I
just have to do with high groups so why
is
equal to one and then we get like a
single vertex and that's like um the
right from secondly last class
where do we derive like if it's Q to the
four then it's like one x
three ways
right well I said at the beginning
is
right yes but last time we described
this q n q m q r q s this is the same
thing
you know the weak attraction formula
I mean if you want you can just
discriminize you know there are two ways
you can derive it we can either
discretize all these integral in time
into these three steps that's one way
you can do something or you can use the
simple equation by part trick that we
introduced this last part chart
and the results
but it's a bit more uh a little less
intuitively that way but improve it
um okay uh so uh now let's interpret the
meaning of this so far it looks like I
can produce something that's not quite
physical
but uh in fact it is
uh provide that you interpret it
carefully
this
it
um if I uh take the integration range
say from zero to the type of d
yes
right so this as we said at the very
beginning this is supposed to be uh
actually
um
uh Matrix element of the uh would rotate
in time evolution of it
uh where a Qi give that there's some
boundary condition that secretly this
this cube is subjective
I would have uh please ignoring up to
now because uh It won't always have
emphasize is not important the valuation
won't be important when we take e to the
Finish
uh but if you like the final Advantage
Edition is that you have to keep track
okay
um
um so uh but we're interested in uh the
people continue limits
uh how does this behave uh well uh let
me see uh
so you can you can post hours as sum
over and uh
where and as always in the basis of the
United States
right so uh
let's say uh dominated this is dominated
by
uh by the ground stage by the ground
state
um
and uh so it's just one term so assuming
that there's a unique advantage point
for the moment
um
um you see that log of G
uh is going to be uh minus e0
plus there's something of the other one
so so whatever that overlap is as long
as it's not a zero generically it would
be between zero and two I or two F it's
just going to be some uh only one number
but adding it to this uh term that the
diverges I think it goes to Infinity
uh so in other words uh if you define
the Z and finite parallel t uh there's a
limit P equals infinity of one over T is
log B now this is actually what is nine
this is equal to the minus the ground
state any
now of course here for comparing CG from
C zero uh if you take the log of C zero
this is G by Z zero you just get uh the
difference between granted energy of the
and Harmony oscillator and the harmonic
acid there is a correction due to the uh
a correction energy uh due to the
interaction term this G uh Q to the
fourth
all right
um
no uh we're in a party function no but
the Gap will be uh if we look at the
excision value of you know QQ we're not
doing that right
this is the perfect function so so uh
you know I haven't discussed yet what
happened whether we have a q a search so
this is just a party button itself
because the third part of the process is
something that you thought may not have
a good interpretation because you run
some some overall normalization but you
see here that actually it does have
interpretation
um and in particular is log is supposed
to linear diverge okay this is the
diversion we're talking about earlier
right position this one's in the future
another episode of the book okay
um so
um
uh okay and uh and we speak from this
discussion the log of z
um
uh is the sum over
uh
kinetic wraps
so this is just by how you would do the
uh expansion in G
um like for the Z itself but instead of
looking at autograph we don't look at
diagrams and then what you'll be
Computing is the log of this effective
function and the result of that
is supposed to be out of this newly
Divergence uh it's supposed to give you
the grass at the energy
okay so now let's uh let's put this to a
formula
so for example
um uh well we have already done this uh
at the order G
order G to the one
uh we have done this already right so so
the g g l equals one
so what is this uh this was uh three
times uh this graph so I won't keep
drawing the purple color so you know
what I mean by this
um and let's write the formula for this
right so this is three times uh minus G
over four factorial which is what we
wrote before integral detailed of G
TaoTao
to the fourth
oh sorry I swear
um okay and uh this equal to
minus g o over eight times uh uh
integral in Tau which of course whatever
this but this is the thing that's
supposed to be the capital t uh then
times this G squared this G remember
this so I recall that uh G so the
harmonic oscillator this was the wrote
one over two Omega e to the minus
Omega one two absolute value uh so the G
power tau is there's one of the virtual
Omega and here when we set Omega to one
for Simplicity but otherwise there's one
word to only
um so actually now let me restore this
on my Independence it doesn't matter
absolutely yeah we're clear to look at
um so uh
so because we conclude that
um the ground state energy
of the anthematic operator take the
following form so e zero uh is uh minus
the apart from the the minor sign here
so the minus this plus G over a times
that one or X Omega Square the strip of
this linear Divergence in time so so it
is G over eight uh one over two Omega
squared and then there'll be some other
G squared time which we're not Computing
at the moment
okay so this is actually a physical
uh result right so it's a you know
um and uh
um
you could recover this from hamiltonian
perturbation Theory uh as you burn in
your intro economy candidate class and
uh I wrote this in the note I think I'm
out of time now so I won't write the
Hamilton the combination of this but
it's a you know if you remember how to
do hamiltonian permission Theory so
first of all there you should be able to
easily recover this in that combination
so the resulting should be equivalent
yes no
um if we look at the origin squared
um isn't that ultimate Bridge even if
you decide
no
uh it was only that averages would only
occur if you have disconnected but
remember here we only have delay
diagrams so
if you
at L for the two right if you have this
diagram
yes that would average like t squared
but we don't have this anymore because
by definition this only keep a mechanic
one so it depending once obviously
things like either this or or maybe this
and you can do that there you go you
find that there's only one Divergence
I'll show you the example right now so I
want something right so this is
the Constitutional constant so the
constant resistible we have three
so you look at this integral
this is Convergence
so you only have one linear Divergence
right the whole point is that because of
this G
um
these two points in the measuring time
cannot be very far separated otherwise
this whole thing is suppressed
exponential
yes
is this the first order
Corrections
yes that's what I said I mean I might
check this using hamiltonian
formulations
oh this is uh this is supposed to be
clear now foreign
foreign
um
uh what's living are you referring to
yeah
is that interesting oh yes uh yes uh and
uh that information is not accessible
from here and you see because
that's weird yeah so but uh next time
we'll discuss uh next lecture we'll
discuss uh the QQ but we're not done
because we started by talking about the
particular value I only covered the
compounded it's so humorous
okay so we're going to set a numerator
next time
what is
it oh
um uh well uh this uh this series
well first of all I didn't use the word
number three I think up to this point
but uh uh the second is that the serious
expansion generally were not um zero
radius convergence uh so
um but nonetheless it is true that uh as
a function of G uh the granted energy if
you look at this Taylor series uh this
will give you the current Taylor series
the same is just the Taylor Swift
doesn't actually convert to the function
itself but this um
uh you know I mean this is not something
uh uh too strange uh you know if you
have a
minus 1 over X
right it's about X greater than zero and
this function
right the standard series identical zero
it's modified
uh but it doesn't doesn't converge into
this function
um this is not the example where the
textures itself I mean we're going to
discuss examples but uh
um
you know
there's a very Elementary examples you
can discuss maybe if you're interested
in the infection but
um we will
most did not touch upon this number of
issues uh in this uh in this semester
the number three aspects is the major
topic and then
I think yeah we'll mostly avoid
applications
that
this uh you know numerically
approximately it's still going to work
as long as it's too small there's a
reason for that and uh let me post one
explanation of that
all right
absolutely
yeah
right now
oh
[Music]
um
differences
I realize